Michael Allen Wingfield papers, 1969-1982 LSC.2327
UCLA Library Special Collections
Michael Allen Wingfield papers
1969-1982
LSC.2327
UCLA Library Special Collections
0.8 linear feet (2 boxes)
Michael Allen Wingfield, former UCLA engineering graduate student, was part of a team responsible for installing the Interface Message Processor (IMP) and creating the first Advanced Research Projects Agency Network (ARPANET) node at the University of California, Los Angeles. He designed the hardware interface linking the Scientific Data Systems (SDS) Sigma 7 computer at UCLA with an IMP to connect to the ARPANET in 1969, making UCLA the first site to receive an IMP. He also implemented Transmission Control Protocol/Internet Protocol (TCP/IP) for Unix, a family of multiuser computer operating systems, in 1979. His papers detail the design specifications of the IMP for ARPANET and the TCP/IP source code for UNIX, and include: handwritten notes, manuals, specifications, computer printouts, and photographs.
Wingfield, Michael Allen
Conditions Governing Access
COLLECTION STORED OFF-SITE AT SRLF: Open for research. All requests to access special collections material must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Donated by Michael Allen Wingfield, 2011.
Custodial History
This collection was acquired by University Archivist Charlotte Brown for a proposed Kleinrock Center for Internet Studies (KCIS) at UCLA in 2011. The former collection number was KCIS003.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 8133227
Biography/History
In June of 1969, Michael Allen Wingfield, an engineering graduate student, was asked by Steve Crocker at UCLA to design the hardware interface between the Scientific Data Systems (SDS) Sigma 7 computer and an Interface Message Processor (IMP) from Bolt, Beranek and Newman (BBN) to connect the UCLA system as the first node on the Advanced Research Projects Agency Network (ARPANET), the precursor to the internet. After reviewing the BBN 1822 IMP interface specification, Wingfield drew up flow charts, logic diagrams, and a test program for the IMP when it was received from BBN in September 1969.
The ARPANET, now the internet, was born on August 30, 1969 when BBN delivered the first IMP to Professor Leonard Kleinrock's Network Measurements Center, a role to which UCLA was assigned as one of the first four sites of the ARPANET to provide either network support services or unique resources. Kleinrock and his students, including Crocker, were deeply involved in the development of techniques to monitor the ARPANET's early performance. Their presence made it natural that UCLA obtained the first node on the ARPANET.
In 1976, Wingfield was hired by BBN, and in 1979, he went on to become a project manager with the National Bureau of Standards to provide a three-node network and the latest protocols. During this time, Vint Cerf, Jon Postel, and others were developing the Transmission Control Protocol/Internet Protocol (TCP/IP) to replace the Network Control Protocol (NCP) in order to better span interconnected networks. When the TCP4 protocol was specified, Wingfield implemented TCP/IP on a UNIX computer using the C programming language.
Scope and Content
The Michael Allen Wingfield papers include handwritten notes, manuals, guides, booklets, photographs which detail the design of the Interface Message Processor (IMP), and computer printouts which include the source code for Transmission Control Protocol/Internet Protocol (TCP/IP) that Wingfield wrote for UNIX.
Organization and Arrangement
The collection is arranged into the following series:
Series 1: Interface Message Processor (IMP)-Host Interface Specifications
Series 2: ARPANET Manuals and Workbooks
Series 3: Source Code for TCP/IP for UNIX
Within Series 2, manuals and documents are arranged chronologically. Within Series 3, the computer code was kept in its existing order to reflect the program design.
Related Material
Leonard Kleinrock papers. Available at UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, UCLA.
Computer Science Department. Student papers, abstracts, and reports. 1965-1977.. Available at Library Special Collections, University Archives, UCLA.
United States. Advanced Research Projects Agency.; Wingfield, Michael Allen -- Archives; ARPANET (Computer network).
- Interface Message Processor (IMP)-Host Interface Specifications, 1969-1978
  Scope and Contents note
  Series 1 contains the specifications for the IMP-Host Interface linking the SDS Sigma 7 computer at UCLA with the BBN Interface Message Processor (IMP) to connect to the ARPANET and includes handwritten notes, manuals, photos, and computer printouts, including a printout of the first test program for the IMP-Host Interface.
  - First program for Testing the IMP-Host Interface, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Photographs of the IMP and IMP-Host Interface, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - IMP-Host Interface 1 Interface Specification, 1969 May (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - IMP-Host Interface 2 Logic Diagrams, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - IMP-Host Interface 3 PIN Name, 1969 October 6 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - IMP-Host Interface 4 PIN Number, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - IMP-Host Interface 5 PIN Name by Board, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - IMP-Host Interface 6 Timing and Flow Charts, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Report No. 1822 IMP 1 Specifications, 1978 May (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Report No. 1822 IMP 2 Appendices, 1978 May (Box 1, Folder 10)
- ARPANET Manuals and Workbooks, 1972-1982
  Series 2 contains manuals detailing scenarios for using the ARPANET at the International Conference on Computer Communication (ICCC), as well as ARPANET and Internet network protocols.
  - Scenarios Booklet for ICCC, 1972 October 24-26 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - ARPA Network Current Network Protocols, 1974 December (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - IP Transition Workbook 1 Introduction, 1982 March (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - IP Transition Workbook 2 Network Level, 1982 March (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - IP Transition Workbook 3 Host Level, 1982 March (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - IP Transition Workbook 4 Application Level, 1982 March (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - IP Transition Workbook 5 Appendices, 1982 March (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - IP Implementation Guide, 1982 August (Box 2, Folder 6)
- TCP/IP Source Code for UNIX, 1979-1980
  Series 3 contains the C programming language source code implementing TCP/IP on a UNIX computer and includes computer printouts of header and C program files and a report on TCP Implementation Status.
  - 1 tcpstru.h, 1979 July 30 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - 2 tcp.h, 1979 February 7 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - 3 hdrmasks.h, 1979 June 5 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - 4 cmdmsg.h, 1979 July 2 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - 5 tcp.c, 1980 June 11 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - 6 psipin.c, 1980 June 11 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 7 psipout.c, 1980 June 11 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - 8 auth.c, 1979 February 14 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - 9 cmdin.c, 1979 July 2 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - 10 tcplib.c, 1979 February 26 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - 11 tcpuser.c, 1979 January 8 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - 12 ftpserv.c, 1979 April 27 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - 13 send.c, 1979 April 27 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - 14 File: Pipe Output, 1978 October 29 - 1979 February 15 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - TCP Implementation Status, 1979 May 3 (Box 2, Folder 21)